Ashwinkumar Ganesan

4833 Carmella Drive, Baltimore, MD - 21227, U.S.A.

(443) 297-7580 • gashwin1@umbc.edu • ashwinkumar.ganesan@yahoo.com http://www.gashwin.com • http://www.linkedin.com/in/gashwin

Summary

I am a PhD Student at the University Of Maryland, Baltimore County. My research focuses on Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning & Data Analytics. I work with Prof. Tim Oates from the Cognition, Robotics, AI & Learning (CORAL) lab.

SKILLS

- Platforms: Linux, Windows.
- Languages & Tools: Python, C, C++ (academic work), Java, Eclipse, Unix Shell Scripting, MongoDB.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science, University of Maryland, Baltimore County, Fall 2017 (expected) CGPA – 3.71 out of 4.0; Advisor – Dr. Tim Oates

Masters of Science in Computer Science, University of Maryland, Baltimore County, August 2012 CGPA – 3.71 out of 4.0; Advisor – Dr. Tim Oates

Thesis – Calculating Representativeness of Geographic Sites Across the World Thesis Committee – Dr. Tim Oates, Tim Finin, Matt Schmill (UMBC) The aim of this research is to understand, how a study or a set of studies of specific geographic areas is representative of other areas of the world. It aims to answer a set of questions which include the definition of representativeness of a geographical site and how the representativeness can be computed.

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science and Engineering, University of Pune, June 2007, Final Year Project: ATHENA – A meta search engine paralized using a grid engine.

WORK HISTORY

Apkudo LLC (Sep. 2012 - August 2014)

Embedded Software Engineer (Location: Baltimore, MD, USA)

- Work on Android operating system customization (and android security).
- Team Coordinator tasked with customer interfacing, implementing agile methodology for the project and designing requirements.

Symantec Corporation (June 2011 to August 2011)

(Research Intern Software Development Intern) (Location: Columbia, MD, USA)

- Designed and developed Test Automation Suite for Symantecs security product i.e. Symantec Critical System Protection (SCSP). Worked on network security functionality of the product.
- Achieved complete automation of network tests on different operating systems and flavours including Redhat, Windows, HP-UX and Solaris.

Niyuj Enterprise Software Solutions (November 2009 to August 2010) Senior Member of Technical Staff (Location: Pune, India)

- Worked on testing of Symantec Security product Critical System Protection including functional and security testing. Gained experience in server administration functions of the various operating systems and Test Execution Cycle for product releases.
- Exposure to tools such as MetaSploit (for security testing) and Aptest (QA and test case management).

Tata Consultancy Services (Sept. 2007 Oct. 2009) Assistant Systems Engineer (Location: Mumbai, India)

- Designed requirements & test cases, performed benchmarking, load testing, stress testing to check
 application performance. Designed and implemented solutions to correct enterprise application
 performance.
- Worked on multiple technologies including HP LoadRunner, HP Performance & Quality Center, Oracle Database, MySQL, Apache Tomcat, HTTP Server and Siebel products. I was a trainer for HP LoadRunner & Performance Testing.

PUBLICATIONS

Journals

• Riley, David R, Sieber, Karsten B, Robinson, Kelly M, White, James Robert, Ganesan, Ashwinkumar, Nourbakhsh, Syrus & Hotopp, Julie C Dunning (2013). Bacteria-human somatic cell lateral gene transfer is enriched in cancer samples. PLoS computational biology, 9, e1003107.

Masters Thesis

• Ganesan, Ashwinkumar (2012). Calculating Representativeness of Geographic Sites Across the World. University of Maryland, Baltimore County (UMBC) - Master's Thesis.

Posters

• Ashwinkumar Ganesan. Calculating Representativeness of Geographic Sites Across the World. 35th Graduate Research Conference UMBC (CSEE winner).

ACADEMIC PROJECTS & ACTIVITIES

- Current CSEE dept. representative and GSA Senator (2014 onwards).
- Teaching Assistant for the Database Management Systems (DBMS), Principles of Artificial Intelligence (Graduate course) & Introduction to Neural Networks.
- Implementing Leader election algorithm using gossip and analysing its efficiency with various network topologies such as clique, circle (with diameters). The project was implemented in Erlang.
- Implementing a game bot for the Google AI Challenge 2010 (Planet wars) using Game Trees and reinforcement learning techniques. The project was implemented in C++.
- Implementing in LISP a program to solve Sudoku problems using Uninformed & Heuristic Search Methods.